Southwest Parks and Monuments Association Records, 1967-1994 MS 463
University of Arizona
Southwest Parks and Monuments Association1967-1994
MS463
Southwest Parks and Monuments Association
4 Linear Feet
Papers, 1967-1994. This collection is comprised of the papers of the Southwest Parks and Monuments Association (SPMA) and the Hubbell Trading Post which is operated by SPMA. Items include business files and SPMA publications. The bulk of the materials include financial ledgers and correspondence. Also included are photographs of the Indian rugs sold by the Hubbell Trading Post, interviews by the rug weavers and some historical documents about the Hubbell Trading Post.
Main Library Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
None
Historical Note
When the National Park Service was created in 1916, several nonprofit organizations (cooperating associations) were formed to support park programs and projects not covered by government funding. By 1936 cooperating associations were formally recognized by Congress, which passed laws enabling them to operate in the national parks. In 1938 the Southwest Monuments Association (later known as the Southwest Parks and Monuments Association (SPMA) was created by the National Park Service and was committed to supporting the education and preservation of 18 national monuments across Arizona and New Mexico
In 2002 the SPMA was renamed the Western National Parks Association (WNPA). The association is located in Tucson, Arizona and now services 66 locations in 12 states and donates over $4 million annually to its national park affiliates. Donations are raised through bookstore sales, membership support, book and publication development, research funding and other educational activities.
The Hubbell Trading Post was sold to the National Park Service in 1967. It is still an active trading post run by the non-profit organization the Western National Parks Association (formerly the Southwest Parks and Monuments Association) for the Park Service.
This Collection is organized into 2 series.
Series I: Hubbell Trading Post
Subseries 1: Correspondences
Subseries 2: Financial
Subseries 3: Photographs of rugs: Indian Rugs
Subseries 4: Research:
Series II: Southwest Parks and Monuments Association
Subseries 1: Committees
Subseries 2: Cooperating Associate (Nation Park Service, N.P.S.)
Subseries 3: Correspondences
Subseries 4: Financial
Subseries 5: Meeting minutes and agenda
Subseries 6: Publications
The bulk of the collection contains correspondences and financial files. The photographs of rugs and research related materials are contained in Hubbell Trading Post series. The documents from different committees are organized by committees and arranged alphabetically in SPMA series. The meeting minutes and agenda and publication are included in SPMA as well.
National parks and reserves.; Monuments.; Navajo Indians – Arizona.; Navajo Rugs.; Hand weaving -- Southwestern States.; Navajo textile fabrics.; Hubbell Trading Post National Historic Site (Ganado, Ariz.).; Southwest Parks and Monument Association.; Southwest Monuments Association.; Western National Parks Association.
- Series I: Hubbell Trading Post (HTP)
  This series is subdivided by document subject, arranged alphabetically, then chronologically. It contains correspondences, HTP financial information, photographs of rugs, and research related materials.
  - Subseries 1: Correspondence
    - General, 1967-1973 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - General, 1974-1978 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - General, 1979-1989 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Personnel, 1975-1982 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Subseries 2: Financial
    - Ledger, 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Ledger, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Ledger, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Ledger, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Ledger, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Ledger (closing entries), 10/1/1978-09/30/1979 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Ledger (journal), 10/1/1972-9/30/1973 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Ledger (journal), 10/1/1972-9/30/1973 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Ledger (journal), 10/1/1973-9/30/1974 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Ledger (journal), 10/1/1974-9/30/1975 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Ledger (journal), 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Ledger (journal), 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Ledger (journal), 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Ledger (journal), 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Ledger (journal), 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Ledger (journal), 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Ledger (rug), 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Ledger (rug + jewelry), 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Ledger (Trial balance), 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Miscellaneous Information: 1967-1987 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Subseries 3: Photographs of rugs
    - Indian rugs #1-2, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Indian rugs #3-4, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Subseries 4: Research
    - Interviews with rug weavers, circa 1985? (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous 1972-1985? (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Project grant, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Project grant, 1986-1987? (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Series II: Southwest Parks and Monument Association (SPMA)
  This series is arranged alphabetically and contains different committee documents, general SPMA correspondence, meeting minutes and agenda, research related materials and publication.
  - Subseries 1: Committees
    - Project grant, 1986-1987? (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Columbus Quincentenary committee, Jan. 1989 – May 1989 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Donation committee, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Donation committee, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Donation committee, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Donation committee, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Donation committee, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Donation committee, 1986-1989 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - SPMA: history and bylaw, 1979, 1984-1988 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Subseries 2: Cooperating Association
    - National Park Service, 1968-1988 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Subseries 3: Correspondences
    - General, 1969-1989 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Avalon McNew file, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Subseries 4: Financial
    - 1967-1986 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - 1987-1989 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Subseries 5: Meeting minutes and agenda
    - 1975-1979 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Subseries 6: Publications
    - 1979-1988 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - 1989 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 1980-1983 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 1984-1985 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, 1986-1987 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Request to publish, 1987-1989 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Research, 1985-1988 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Sand dunes, 1981-1994 (Box 4, Folder 13)